"Two households, both alike in dignity,
in fair Verona, where we lay our scene,
from ancient grudge
break to new mutiny,
where civil blood
makes civil hands unclean.
From forth the fatal loins
of these two foes
a pair of star-cross'd lovers
take their life."
The Capulets, the Capulets.
The Capulets.
The Montagues.
Here come the Capulets.
Be patient. Take no note.
- The House of Montague, our foe.
- Soft.
Keep the peace.
I strike quickly, being moved,
when a dog of the House of Montague
moves me.
Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?
- I do bite my thumb, sir.
- Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?
- Is the law on our side if I say ay?
- No.
No, sir, I do not bite my thumb at you, sir,
but I do bite my thumb, sir.
- Do you quarrel, sir?
- Quarrel, sir?
- No, sir.
- If you do, sir, I am for you.
I serve as good a man as you.
No better.
- Say "better."
- Yes, better.
- You lie.
- Draw, if you be men.
Part, fools!
Put up your swords.
What? Art thou drawn amongst
these heartless hinds?
Turn thee, Benvolio, look upon thy death.
I do but keep the peace.
Put up thy sword
or manage it to part these men with me.
What? Drawn, and talk of peace?
I hate the word as I hate hell,
all Montagues and thee.
Have at thee, coward.
Rebellious subjects, enemies to peace.
Will they not hear?
What ho, you men, you beasts,
on pain of torture.
Throw your mis-temper'd weapons
to the ground
and hear the sentence
of your moved Prince.
Three civil brawls, bred of an airy word
by thee, old Capulet,
and Montague, have thrice disturb'd
the quiet of our streets.
If ever you disturb our streets again,
your lives
shall pay the forfeit of the peace.
For this time, all the rest depart away.
You, Capulet, shall go along with me,
and, Montague,
come you this afternoon
to know our further pleasure in this case.
Once more, on pain of death,
all men depart.
But Montague is bound as well as I,
in penalty alike.
And 'tis not hard, I think,
for men as old as we to keep the peace.
Of honorable reckoning are you both.
And pity it is you've lived at odds so long.
But now, my lord,
what say you to my suit?
But saying o'er what I have said before.
My child is yet a stranger in the world.
But woo her, gentle Paris, get her heart.
This night I hold an old accustom'd feast,
whereto I have invited
many a guest such as I love,
and you, among the store, one more,
most welcome, makes my number more.
Sirrah.
Sirrah!
Go, trudge about through fair Verona,
find those persons out
whose names are written there,
and to them say my house
and welcome on their pleasure stay.
Nurse.
Where's my daughter?
Call her forth to me.
I bade her come. What, lamb.
What, ladybird.
God forbid. Where's this girl?
What, Juliet!
Madam, what is your will?
This is the matter.
Nurse, give leave awhile.
We must talk in secret.
Nurse, come back again.
I have remember'd me,
thou'st hear our counsel.
Thou know'st my daughter's
of a pretty age.
Faith, I can tell her age unto an hour.
Susan and she, God rest
all Christian souls, were of an age.
Well, Susan is with God.
She was too good for me.
But as I said,
my lord and you were then at Mantua.
For then she could stand alone.
Nay, by the rood,
she could have run and waddled all about.
For even the day before,
she broke her brow.
And then my husband,
God be with his soul, he was a merry man,
took up the child. "Yea," quoth he,
"Dost thou fall upon thy face?
"Thou wilt fall backward when thou hast
more wit. Wilt thou not, Jule?"
And, by my halidom, the pretty wretch
left crying, and said, "Ay."
To see now how a jest may come about.
I warrant, and I should live
a thousand years, I never should forget it.
"Wilt thou not, Jule?" quoth he.
And, pretty fool, it stinted and said, "Ay."
Enough of this. I pray thee, hold thy peace.
Peace, I have done.
God mark thee to his grace.
Thou wast the prettiest babe
that e'er I nursed.
And I might live to see thee married once,
I have my wish.
Marry, that "marry" is the very theme
I came to talk of.
Tell me, daughter Juliet,
how stands your disposition
to be married?
It is an honor that I dream not of.
Well, think of marriage now.
The valiant Paris seeks you for his love.
My will to her consent is but a part.
Oh, a man, young lady.
Lady, such a man as all the world.
Why, he's a man of wax.
Verona's summer hath not such a flower.
Nay, he's a flower. In faith, a very flower.
What say you?
Can you love the gentleman?
This night you shall
behold him at our feast.
Speak briefly. Can you like of Paris' love?
I'll look to like, if looking liking move.
But no more deep will I endart mine eye
than your consent
gives strength to make it fly.
Good morrow, cousin.
Is the day so young?
But new struck 9:00.
And here I hit it right,
our Romeo has not been in bed tonight.
Ay me, sad hours seem long.
What sadness lengthens Romeo's hours?
Not having that which having
makes them short.
- In love?
- Out.
- Of love?
- Out of her favor where I am in love.
Jesu Maria ! What a deal of brine hath
washed thy sallow cheek for Rosaline.
Rosaline.
Dost thou not laugh?
No, coz, I rather weep.
- Good heart, at what?
- At thy good heart's oppression.
Why, such is love's transgression.
Love is a smoke
raised with the fume of sighs,
being purged,
a fire sparkling in lover's eyes,
being vexed,
a sea nourished with lover's tears.
What is it else?
A madness most discreet,
a choking gall and a preserving sweet.
And, in strong proof of chastity well arm'd,
from love's weak childish bow
she lives unharmed.
Be ruled by me. Forget to think of her.
Oh, teach me how I should forget to think.
By giving liberty unto thine eyes.
Examine other beauties.
He that is strucken blind
cannot forget the precious treasure
of his eyesight lost.
Show me a mistress that is passing fair,
what doth her beauty serve but as a note
where I may read
who pass'd that passing fair?
Tut, man, one fire burns out
another's burning.
One pain is lessen'd by another's anguish.
Take thou some new infection to thy eye,
and the rank poison of the old will die.
Romeo, art thou mad?
No, not mad,
but bound more than a madman is.
Shut up in prison, kept without my food,
whipp'd and tormented.
Good den, good fellow.
God gi' good den. I pray, sir, can you read?
Ay, my own fortune in my misery.
Well, perhaps you have learn'd it
without book,
but I pray, sir,
can you read anything you see?
Ay, if I know the letters and the language.
- Ye say honestly. Rest you merry.
- Stay, fellow, I can read.
"Signor Martino and his wife
and daughters,
"County Anselme
and his beauteous sisters,
"the lady widow of Vitruvio,
"Signor Placentio and his lovely nieces,
"Mercutio and his brother Valentine.
"Signor Valentio and his cousin Tybalt."
Tybalt.
"My fair niece Rosaline."
A fair assembly.
Whither should they come?
- Up.
- Whither?
- To supper, to our house.
- To whose house?
- My master's.
- Yes, indeed,
I should have asked you that before.
Now I'll tell you without asking.
My master is the great rich Capulet.
And if you be not
of the House of Montague,
I pray, come and crush a cup of wine.
Rest you merry.
At this same ancient feast of Capulet's
sups the fair Rosaline
whom thou so lov'st
with all the admired beauties of Verona.
Go thither, and with unattainted eye
compare her face
with some that I shall show.
- I will make thee think thy swan a crow.
- One fairer than my love?
The all-seeing sun ne'er saw her match
since first the world begun.
I'll go along, no such sight to be shown,
but to rejoice in splendor of mine own.
- Mercutio.
- Come, supper is served.
I shall not budge.
- Come, let's away.
- I shall not budge for no man's pleasure.
Give me a torch. I am not for this ambling.
Nay, gentle Romeo,
we must have you dance.
Not I, believe me.
You have dancing shoes with nimble soles.
I have a soul of lead so stakes me
to the ground I cannot move.
You are a lover, borrow Cupid's wings
and soar with them
above a common bound.
Come, let us enter, and no sooner in,
but every man betake him to his legs.
And we mean well
in going to this masque.
- But 'tis no wit to go.
- Why, may one ask?
I dream'd a dream last night.
- And so did I.
- What was yours?
That dreamers often lie.
In bed asleep,
while they do dream things true.
O, then,
I see Queen Mab hath been with you.
She is the fairies' midwife,
and she comes in shape
no bigger than an agate stone
upon the forefinger of an alderman.
Drawn with a team of little atomies
athwart men's noses as they lie asleep.
Her wagon spokes
made of long spinner's legs.
The covers, of the wings of grasshoppers.
The traces, of the smallest spider's web.
The collars,
of the moonshine's watery beams.
Her whip, of cricket's bone.
The lash, of film.
Her waggoner, a small gray-coated gnat,
not half so big as a round little worm
prick'd from the lazy finger of a maid.
Her chariot is an empty hazelnut,
made by the joiner squirrel or old grub,
time out of mind the fairies' coach-makers.
And in this state
she gallops night by night
through lovers' brains,
and then they dream on love.
O'er courtiers' knees,
who dream on curtsies straight.
O'er lawyers' fingers
who straight dream on fees.
O'er ladies lips,
who straight on kisses dream.
Sometimes she gallops
o'er a courtier's nose,
and then dreams he of smelling out a suit.
And sometimes come she
with a tithe-pig's tail
tickling a parson's nose as he lies asleep,
then dreams he of another benefice.
Sometimes she driveth
o'er a soldier's neck,
and then dreams he of cutting foreign
throats, of breaches, ambuscadoes,
Spanish blades,
of healths five fathom deep.
And then anon drums in his ears,
at which he starts and wakes,
and being thus frighted swears a prayer
or two and sleeps again.
- This is that very Mab. This is she...
- Peace, peace, Mercutio, peace.
Thou talk'st of nothing.
True, I talk of dreams,
which are the children of an idle brain,
begot of nothing but vain fantasy,
as thin of substance as the air,
and more inconstant than the wind.
This wind you talk of
blows us from ourselves.
Supper is done
and we shall come too late.
I fear, too early.
For my mind misgives some consequence
yet hanging in the stars
shall bitterly begin his fearful date
with this night's revels.
But he, that hath the steerage
of my course, direct my sail.
On, lusty gentlemen.
Strike drum.
Welcome, gentlemen.
I have seen the day
that I have worn a visor,
and could tell a whispering tale
in a fair lady's ear,
such as would please.
'Tis gone, 'tis gone, 'tis gone.
You are welcome, gentlemen.
The fair Rosaline whom thou so lov'st.
She hath forsworn to love.
Thou canst not teach me to forget.
What lady's that which doth enrich
the hand of yonder knight?
I know not, sir.
Oh, she doth teach
the torches to burn bright.
It seems she hangs upon the cheek
of night like a rich jewel in an Ethiop's ear.
Did my heart love till now?
Forswear it, sight.
For I ne'er saw true beauty till this night.
This, by his voice, should be a Montague.
Fetch me my rapier, boy.
What? Dares the slave come hither
cover'd with an antic face
to fleer and scorn at our solemnity?
Why, how now, kinsman?
Wherefore storm you so?
Uncle, this is a Montague.
Our foe,
a villain that is hither come in spite
to scorn at our solemnity this night.
- Young Romeo, is it?
- 'Tis he, that villain Romeo.
Content thee, gentle coz, let him alone.
I wouldn't for the wealth of all this town
here in my house do him disparagement.
Therefore be patient, take no note of him.
- I'll not endure him.
- He shall be endur'd.
What, goodman boy. I say, he shall.
Go to. Am I the master here or you?
Go to. You'll not endure him.
- Why, Uncle, 'tis a shame.
- Go to. Go to.
You are a saucy boy.
I will withdraw.
But this intrusion shall, now
seeming sweet, convert to bitterest gall.
If I profane with my unworthiest hand
this holy shrine,
the gentle fine is this.
My lips, two blushing pilgrims,
ready stand to smooth that rough touch
with a tender kiss.
Good pilgrim,
you do wrong your hand too much.
For saints have hands
that pilgrims' hands do touch,
and palm to palm is holy palmers' kiss.
Have not saints lips,
and holy palmers, too?
Ay, pilgrim,
lips that they must use in prayer.
O, then, dear saint,
let lips do what hands do.
They pray, grant thou,
lest faith turn to despair.
Saints do not move,
though grant for prayers' sake.
Then move not,
while my prayers' effect I take.
Thus from my lips by thine,
my sin is purged.
Then have my lips the sin
that they have took.
Sin from my lips?
Oh, trespass sweetly urged.
Give me my sin again.
Madam.
Your mother craves a word with you.
What is her mother?
Marry, bachelor,
her mother is the lady of the house,
and a good lady, and a wise, and virtuous.
I nursed her daughter
that you talked withal.
Is she a Capulet?
O dear account.
My life is my foe's debt.
Away, be gone. The sport is at the best.
Ay, so I fear. The more is my unrest.
Come hither, nurse.
What is yond gentleman?
The son and heir of old Tiberio.
What's he that now is going out of door?
Marry, that, I think, be young Petruchio.
What's he that follows there?
- I know not.
- Go, ask his name.
His name is Romeo, and a Montague.
- The only son of your great enemy.
- A Montague?
My only love sprung from my only hate.
Too early seen unknown,
- and known too late.
- What's this, what's this?
A rhyme I learned e'en now
of one I danced withal.
Come, let's away.
The strangers all are gone.
Romeo.
Romeo. My cousin, Romeo.
He is wise, and, on my life,
hath stolen him home to bed.
He ran this way. Call, good Mercutio.
Nay, I'll conjure, too.
Romeo. Humors. Madman. Passion. Lover.
Appear thou in the likeness of a sigh.
Speak but one rhyme, and I am satisfied.
Cry but, "Ah, me."
Pronounce but "Iove" and "dove."
He heareth not. He stirreth not.
He moveth not.
The ape is dead,
and I must conjure him.
I conjure thee by Rosaline's bright eyes,
by her high forehead and her scarlet lip,
by her fine foot,
straight leg and quivering thigh,
and the demesnes that there adjacent lie,
that in thy likeness thou appear to us.
Come, he hath hid himself
among these trees.
Blind is his love and best befits the dark.
Romeo, good night. I'll to my truckle-bed.
This field-bed is too cold for me to sleep.
He jests at scars that never felt a wound.
But, soft. What light
through yonder window breaks?
It is the east, and Juliet is the sun.
It is my lady. Oh, it is my love.
Oh, that she knew she were.
See how she leans her cheek
upon her hand.
Oh, that I were a glove upon that hand
that I might touch that cheek.
Ay me!
Oh, speak again, bright angel.
For thou art as glorious to this night,
being o'er my head,
as is a winged messenger of heaven.
O Romeo. Romeo.
Wherefore art thou Romeo?
Deny thy father and refuse thy name.
Or, if thou wilt not, be but sworn my love,
and I'll no longer be a Capulet.
Shall I hear more, or shall I speak at this?
'Tis but thy name that is my enemy.
What's in a name?
That which we call a rose
by any other name would smell as sweet.
So Romeo would,
were he were not Romeo called,
retain that dear perfection
which he owes without that title.
Romeo, doff thy name,
and for that name which is no part of thee,
take all myself.
I take thee at thy word.
Call me but love, and I'll be new baptized.
What man art thou,
that thus be screened in night,
so stumblest on my counsel?
By a name
I know not how to tell thee who I am.
My name, dear saint, is hateful to myself,
because it is an enemy to thee.
My ears have not yet drunk a hundred
words of that tongue's utterance,
yet I know the sound.
Art thou not Romeo, and a Montague?
Neither, fair maid, if either thee dislike.
How camest thou hither, tell me,
and wherefore?
The orchard walls are high
and hard to climb
and the place death, considering who thou
art, if any of my kinsmen find thee here.
With love's light wings
did I o'er-perch these walls.
For stony limits cannot hold love out,
and what love can do,
that dares love attempt.
Therefore thy kinsmen are no let to me.
If they do see thee, they will murder thee.
Alack, there lies more peril in thine eye
than twenty of their swords.
Look thou but sweet,
and I am proof against their enmity.
I would not for the world
they saw thee here.
I have night's cloak to hide me
from their eyes,
and but thou love me,
let them find me here.
By whose direction
found'st thou out this place?
By Love's,
that first did prompt me to inquire.
He lent me counsel, and I lent him eyes.
I am no pilot.
Yet, wert thou as far as that vast shore
washed by the farthest sea,
I should adventure for such merchandise.
Thou know'st the mask of night
is on my face.
Else would a maiden blush
bepaint my cheek
for that which thou hast heard me
speak tonight.
Fain would I dwell on form,
fain, fain deny what I have spoke:
but farewell compliment.
Dost thou love me?
I know thou wilt say ay,
and I will take thy word.
Yet, if thou swear'st,
thou mayst prove false.
At lovers' perjuries they say Jove laughs.
O gentle Romeo.
If thou dost love,
pronounce it faithfully.
Or if thou think'st I am too quickly won,
I'll frown and be perverse,
and say thee nay, so thou wilt woo.
Else not for the world.
In truth, fair Montague,
I am too fond.
Therefore pardon me,
and not impute this yielding to light love,
which the dark night hath so discovered.
Lady, by yonder blessed moon I swear
that tips with silver
all these fruit tree tops.
Oh, swear not by the moon,
the inconstant moon,
that monthly changes in her circled orb,
lest that thy love prove likewise variable.
- What shall I swear by?
- Do not swear at all.
Or, if thou wilt,
swear by thy gracious self,
which is the god of my idolatry,
and I'll believe thee.
If my heart's dear love...
Well, do not swear.
Although I joy in thee,
I have no joy of this contract tonight.
It is too rash, too unadvised, too sudden.
Too like the lightning, which doth cease
to be ere one can say it lightens.
- Sweet, good night.
- Wilt thou leave me so unsatisfied?
What satisfaction
cans't thou have tonight?
The exchange of thy love's faithful vow
for mine.
I gave thee mine
before thou dids't request it.
And yet I would it were to give again.
Wouldst thou withdraw it?
For what purpose, love?
But to be frank, and give it thee again.
My bounty is as boundless as the sea,
my love as deep.
The more I give to thee, the more I have,
for both are infinite.
I hear some noise within. Dear love, adieu.
Juliet.
Anon, good nurse.
Sweet Montague, be true.
Stay but a little, I will come again.
O blessed, blessed night.
I am afeard, being in night,
all this is but a dream,
too flattering-sweet to be substantial.
Three words, dear Romeo,
and good night, indeed.
If that thy bent of love be honorable,
thy purpose marriage,
send me word tomorrow by one
that I'll procure to come to thee,
where and what time
thou wilt perform the rite.
And all my fortunes at thy foot I'll lay
and follow thee, my lord,
throughout the world.
- Madam.
- I come anon.
But if thou mean'st not well,
I do beseech thee...
- Madam.
- By and by, I come.
To cease thy suit
and leave me to my grief.
Tomorrow will I send.
So thrive my soul.
A thousand times good night.
A thousand times the worse,
to want thy light.
Romeo. Romeo.
- It is my soul that calls upon my name.
- Romeo.
How silver-sweet
sound lovers' tongues by night,
like softest music to attending ears.
My dear.
I have forgot why I did call thee back.
Let me stand here till thou remember it.
I shall forget,
to have thee still stand there,
remembering how I love thy company.
And I'll still stay, to have thee still forget,
forgetting any other home but this.
'Tis almost morning.
I would have thee gone,
and yet no further than a wanton's bird,
who lets it hop a little from her hand
and with a silk thread plucks it back again,
- so loving jealous of his liberty.
- I would I were thy bird.
Sweet, so would I.
Yet, I should kill thee
with much cherishing.
Good night. Good night.
Parting is such sweet sorrow
that I shall say good night
till it be morrow.
Sleep dwell upon thine eyes,
peace in thy breast.
Would I were sleep and peace,
so sweet to rest.
Where the devil should this Romeo be?
Came he not home last night?
Not to his father's. I spoke with his men.
Why, that same pale,
hard-hearted wench, that Rosaline,
torments him so he will sure run mad.
Tybalt, the kinsman of old Capulet,
has sent a letter to his father's house.
- A challenge, on my life.
- Romeo will answer it.
Alas, poor Romeo. He is already dead.
Stabbed with a white wench's black eye,
shot through the ear with a love song.
The very pin of his heart,
cleft with the blind bow-boy's butt-shaft.
- And is he a man to encounter Tybalt?
- Why, what is Tybalt?
More than prince of cats, I can tell you.
Oh, he is the courageous captain
of compliments.
These fashion mongers,
these pardonnez-mois.
Their bons, their bons.
He fights as you sing prick-songs.
Keeps time, distance and proportion,
one, two and the third in your bosom.
The very butcher of a silk button.
A duelist, a duelist, the immortal passado.
The punto reverso. The hay.
Here comes Romeo.
Without his roe, like a dried herring.
O flesh, flesh, how thou art fishified.
Signor Romeo, bonjour.
You gave us
the counterfeit fairly last night.
Good morrow to you both.
What counterfeit did I give you?
- The slip, sir, the slip.
- Pardon, good Mercutio.
My business was great, and in such a case
as mine a man may strain courtesy.
That's as much as to say,
such a case as yours,
constrains a man to bow in the hams.
- Meaning, to curtsey.
- Thou hast most kindly hit it.
A most courteous exposition.
Why, is this not better now
than groaning for love?
Now art thou sociable,
now art thou Romeo.
A sail, a sail.
Two, two, a shirt and a smock.
Peter.
- Anon.
- My fan, Peter.
Good Peter, to hide her face.
God ye good morrow, gentlemen.
- God ye good day, fair gentlewoman.
- Is it good day?
'Tis no less, I tell you,
for the bawdy hand of the dial
is even now upon the prick of noon.
Out upon you. What a man are you!
Gentlemen, can any of you tell me
where I may find the young Romeo?
I can tell you.
I'm the youngest of that name,
for want of a worse.
If you be he, sir,
I desire some confidence with you.
The young lady...
The young lady bade me... Get back!
She will invite him to some supper.
A bawd, a bawd, a bawd.
Farewell, ancient lady! Farewell.
Lady, lady, lady!
Marry, farewell. I pray you, sir,
what saucy merchant was this?
A gentleman, nurse,
who loves to hear himself talk.
And to speak anything against me,
I'll take him down
and a' were lustier than he is,
and twenty such Jacks.
And I cannot, I'll find those that shall.
Scurvy knave.
I am none of his flirt-gills.
And thou must stand by, too, and suffer
every knave to use me at his pleasure.
I saw no man use you at his pleasure.
If I had, my weapon should quickly
have been out, I warrant.
I dare draw as soon as another man
if I see occasion in a good quarrel
and the law on my side.
Now, afore God, I am so vexed
that every part about me quivers.
Scurvy knave!
Pray you, sir, a word.
As I told you,
my young lady bade me inquire you out.
- Yes.
- What she bade me say,
- I'll keep to myself.
- Oh, no.
But first let me tell you.
If you should lead her into
a fool's paradise, as they say,
it were a very gross kind of behavior,
as they say,
for the gentlewoman is young,
and, therefore,
if you should deal double with her...
I protest. I protest.
Good heart and faith,
I will tell her as much.
Lord, lord, she will be a joyful woman.
What wilt thou tell her, nurse?
I will tell her, sir, that you do protest
which, as I take it,
is a gentleman-like offer.
Bid her devise some means
to come to shrift this afternoon.