There she shall at Friar Laurence's cell
be shrived and married.
- Here. Here is for thy pains.
- No, truly, sir, not a penny.
Go to, I say you shall.
This afternoon, sir, she shall be there.
- Commend me to thy lady.
- Ay, a thousand times.
- Peter!
- Anon.
Take my fan and go before.
And apace, apace.
The clock struck 9:00
when I did send the nurse.
In half an hour she promised to return.
Perchance she cannot meet him.
That's not so.
She is lame.
Love's heralds should be thoughts,
which ten times faster glide
than the sun's beams.
From 9:00 till 12:00 is three long hours.
And yet she is not come.
Had she affections
and warm youthful blood,
she'd be as swift in motion as a ball.
My words would bandy her
to my sweet love, and his to me.
O God, she comes.
O honey nurse, what news?
Hast thou met with him?
- Send thy man away.
- Peter, stay at the gate.
- Anon.
- Now, good, sweet nurse.
- O Lord, why look'st thou sad?
- I am aweary, give me leave a while.
Fie, how my bones ache.
What a jaunt have I had.
I would thou hadst my bones
and I thy news.
Nay, come, I pray thee, speak.
Good, good nurse, speak.
Jesu. What haste?
Can you not stay awhile?
Do you not see that I am out of breath?
How are thou out of breath,
when thou hast breath to say to me
that thou art out of breath?
Is thy news good or bad?
Answer to that.
Let me be satisfied, is it good or bad?
Well, you have made a simple choice.
You know not how to choose a man.
Go thy ways, wench, serve God.
- What, have you dined at home?
- No, no.
What says he of our marriage?
What of that?
Lord, how my head aches.
What a head have I!
It beats as it would fall in twenty pieces.
Oh, my back.
The other side.
Beshrew your heart
for sending me about to catch my death
with jaunting up and down.
In faith, I am sorry that thou art not well.
O sweet, sweet, sweet nurse,
tell me, what says my love?
Your love says,
like an honest gentleman and
a courteous and a kind and a handsome
and I warrant, a virtuous...
Where is your mother?
Where is my mother?
Why, she is within. Where should she be?
How oddly thou repliest!
"Your love says, like an honest gentleman,
where is your mother?"
Oh, God's lady dear! Are you so hot?
Marry, come up, I trow.
Is this the poultice for my aching bones?
Henceforward, do your messages yourself!
Come, what says Romeo?
- Have you got leave to go to shrift today?
- I have.
Then hie you hence
to Friar Laurence's cell,
there stays a husband to make you a wife.
Now comes the wanton blood
up in your cheeks.
They'll be scarlet straight at any news.
Hie you to church, go. I'll to dinner.
Hie you to the cell!
Hie to high fortune.
Honest nurse, farewell.
- Good den, Father.
- Benedicite.
God mark thee to His grace, young son.
I love thy company.
- Where hast thou been?
- I have been feasting with mine enemy,
where on a sudden one hath wounded me
that's by me wounded.
Both our remedies within thy help
and holy physic lies.
Be plain, good son.
Then plainly know, my heart's dear love
is set on the fair daughter of rich Capulet.
As mine on hers, so hers is set on mine,
and this I pray that thou consent
to marry us this day.
Holy Saint Francis, what a change is here.
Is Rosaline, that thou didst love so dear,
so soon forsaken?
I pray thee, chide me not.
Amen. Amen.
So smile the heavens upon this holy act,
that after hours with sorrow chide us not.
But come what sorrow can,
it cannot countervail the exchange of joy
that one short minute gives me
in her sight.
These violent delights have violent ends
and in their triumph die,
like fire and powder,
which as they kiss, consume.
Do thou but close our hands
with holy words,
then love-devouring death do what it dare.
It is enough I may but call her mine.
And this alliance may so happy prove,
to turn your household's rancor
to pure love.
Here comes the lady.
Oh, so light a foot will ne'er wear out
the everlasting flint.
Juliet.
Good even to my ghostly confessor.
Romeo shall thank thee,
daughter, for us both.
Ah, Juliet.
If the measure of thy joy
be heaped like mine,
and that thy skill be more to blazon it,
then sweeten with thy breath
this neighbor air,
and let rich music's tongue unfold
the imagined happiness
that both receive in either
by this dear encounter.
My true love is grown to such excess,
I cannot sum up half my wealth.
Come, come with me,
and we will make short work.
For by your leaves,
you shall not stay alone
till holy church incorporate two in one.
I pray thee, good Mercutio, let's retire.
The day is hot, the Capulets abroad.
And if we meet,
we shall not escape a brawl.
Thou are like one of those fellows that,
when he enters the confines of a tavern,
claps me a sword upon the table and says,
"God send me no need of thee."
Am I like such a fellow?
Come, come, thou are as hot a Jack
in thy mood as any man in Italy.
If there were two such, we'd have none
shortly, for one would kill the other.
Thou. Thou wilt quarrel with a man
who hath a hair more
or a hair less in his beard than thou hast.
Thou wilt quarrel with a man
for cracking nuts,
having no other reason
than because thou hast hazel eyes.
Thou hast quarreled with a man
for coughing in the street
because he has awakened thy dog
that has lain asleep in the sun.
And yet you will tutor me from quarreling.
And I were so apt to quarrel as thou art.
- By my head, here come the Capulets.
- By my heel, I care not.
Follow me close,
for I will speak with them.
Gentlemen, good den.
A word with one of you.
And but one word with one of us?
Couple it with something.
Make it a word and a blow.
You shall find me apt enough to that, sir,
and you will give me occasion.
Could you not take some occasion
without giving?
- Mercutio, thou consorts with Romeo.
- Consort!
What dost thou make us, minstrels?
An thou make minstrels of us,
look to hear nothing but discords.
Here's my fiddlestick.
Here's that'll make you dance.
Zounds, consort.
Well, peace be with you, sir.
Here comes my man.
Romeo!
The love I bear thee
can afford no better term than this.
Thou art a villain.
Tybalt,
the reason that I have to love thee
doth much excuse the appertaining rage
to such a greeting.
Villain am I none,
therefore farewell.
I see thou know'st me not.
Boy, this shall not excuse
the injuries thou hast done me.
Therefore, turn and draw.
I do protest, I never injured thee,
but love thee
better than thou canst devise,
till thou shall know the reason of my love.
And so, good Capulet, which name
I tender as dearly as mine own,
be satisfied.
Mercutio.
O calm, dishonorable, vile submission.
Alla stoccata carries it away.
Tybalt!
- You rat catcher. Will you walk?
- What wouldst thou have with me?
Good king of cats,
nothing but one of your nine lives.
- I am for you.
- Gentle Mercutio, put thy rapier up.
Come, sir, your passado.
Draw, Benvolio. Beat down their weapons.
Gentlemen, for shame,
forbear this outrage.
Well, I'm hurt.
A plague on both your houses.
I am sped.
- What, is he gone and hath nothing?
- What, art thou hurt?
Ay, a scratch, a scratch.
Marry, 'tis enough. Where is my page?
Go, villain, fetch a surgeon.
Courage, man. The hurt cannot be much.
No, 'tis not so deep as a well,
nor so wide as a church door,
but 'tis enough. It will serve.
Ask for me tomorrow
and you shall find me a grave man.
I'm peppered, I warrant, for this world.
Zounds, a dog, a rat, a mouse,
a cat to scratch a man to death.
A braggart, a rogue, a villain
that fights by the book of arithmetic.
Why the devil came you between us?
- I was hurt under your arm.
- I thought all for the best.
Help me into some house, Benvolio,
or I shall faint.
A plague on both your houses.
They've made worms' meat of me.
I have it and soundly, too.
Your houses.
Your...
Brave Mercutio's dead.
Ah, sweet Juliet.
Thy beauty hath made me effeminate.
And in my temper softened valor's steel.
Tybalt!
Now, Tybalt,
take the villain back again
that late thou gavest me.
For Mercutio's soul
is but a little way above our heads,
waiting for thine to keep him company.
Either thou or I or both must go with him.
This shall determine that!
Romeo, away! Be gone!
Stand not amazed.
The prince will doom thee death
if thou are taken!
Hence, be gone! Away!
I am fortune's fool.
Why dost thou stay?
Benvolio!
Who began this bloody fray?
O noble prince, an envious thrust
from Tybalt hit the life of stout Mercutio,
then Tybalt fled,
but by and by comes Romeo,
and to it they go like lightning.
Ere I could draw to part them,
was stout Tybalt slain,
and, as he fell, did Romeo turn and fly.
And for that offense,
immediately do we exile him hence.
I will be deaf to pleadings and excuses,
therefore use none.
But Romeo hence in haste,
else when he's found that hour is his last.
Romeo, come forth.
Father, what news?
What...
What is the Prince's doom?
Hence from Verona art thou banished.
Be patient,
for the world is broad and wide.
There is no world without Verona walls,
but purgatory, torture, hell itself.
- This is dear mercy, and thou seest it not.
- 'Tis torture and not mercy.
Heaven is here, where Juliet lives.
And every cat and dog and little mouse,
every unworthy thing,
live here in heaven and may look on her,
but Romeo may not.
Hadst thou no poison mixed,
no sharp-ground knife, no sudden mean
of death, though ne'er so mean,
but banished to kill me?
How hast thou the heart,
being a divine, a ghostly confessor,
a sin absolver and my friend professed,
to mangle me with that word "banished"?
Thou fond madman,
hear me but speak a word.
Thou canst not speak of that
thou dost not feel!
Wert thou as young as I,
Juliet thy love, an hour but married,
Tybalt murdered, doting like me,
and, like me, banished,
then might'st thou speak.
So tedious is this day
as is the night before some festival
to an impatient child
that hath new robes
and may not wear them.
Spread thy close curtain,
love-performing night,
that runaway's eyes may wink,
and Romeo leap to these arms,
untalked of and unseen.
Come, gentle night.
Come, loving, black-browed night.
Give me my Romeo.
And, when he shall die,
take him and cut him out in little stars.
And he will make the face of heaven
so fine
that all the world will be in love with night
and pay no worship to the garish sun.
Oh, I have bought the mansion of a love,
but not possessed it.
Now, nurse, what news? What news?
Why dost thou wring thy hands?
He's dead, he's dead, he's dead.
We are undone, lady, we are undone.
Tybalt is dead and Romeo banished.
Romeo that killed him, he is banished.
O God, did Romeo's hand
shed Tybalt's blood?
It did, it did. Alas the day. It did.
O serpent heart, hid with a flowering face.
Beautiful tyrant.
Fiend angelical.
Just opposite to what thou justly seem'st.
A damned saint, an honorable villain!
There's no trust, no faith,
no honesty in men.
Shame come to Romeo.
Blistered be thy tongue for such a wish.
He was not born to shame.
Oh, and what a beast was I
to chide at him.
Will you speak well of him
that killed your cousin?
Shall I speak ill of him that is my husband?
Ah, poor my lord,
what tongue shall smooth thy name
when I, thy three hours wife,
have mangled it?
My husband lives,
that Tybalt would have slain.
And Tybalt's dead,
that would have slain my husband.
All this is comfort. Wherefore weep I then?
Tybalt is dead and Romeo banished.
That "banished,"
that one word "banished"
hath slain ten thousand Tybalts!
"Romeo is banished! "
Oh, to speak that word is father, mother,
Tybalt, Romeo, Juliet,
all slain, all dead.
I'll find Romeo to comfort you.
I wot well where he is. Hark ye,
your Romeo will be here at night.
He's hid in Laurence's cell.
Oh, find him.
Give this ring to my true knight
and bid him come to take his last farewell.
- Whence come you? What's your will?
- I come from Lady Juliet.
Welcome, then.
Nurse.
Spakest thou of Juliet? How is it with her?
Oh, she says nothing, sir,
but weeps and weeps.
And now falls on her bed.
And then starts up and Tybalt calls,
and then on Romeo cries.
As if that name, shot from the deadly level
of a gun, did murder her.
As that name's cursed hand
murdered her kinsman.
Oh, tell me, Friar.
Tell me, in what vile part of this anatomy
doth my name lodge?
Tell me, that I may sack
the hateful mansion.
Hold thy desperate hand. Art thou a man?
Thy wild acts denote
the unreasonable fury of a beast.
Hast thou slain Tybalt?
Wilt thou slay thyself?
And slay thy lady that in thy life lives,
by doing damned hate upon thyself?
Rouse thee, man.
Thy Juliet is alive.
Go, get thee to thy love, as was decreed,
ascend her chamber,
hence and comfort her.
But look thou stay not
till the watch be set,
for then thou canst not pass to Mantua.
There thou shalt live till we can find
a time to blaze your marriage,
reconcile your friends, beg pardon
of the Prince, and call thee back
with twenty hundred thousand times more
joy than thou went'st forth in lamentation.
Wilt thou be gone? It is not yet near day.
It was the nightingale and not the lark
that pierced the fearful hollow of thine ear.
Nightly she sings
on yon pomegranate tree.
And believe me, love,
it was the nightingale.
It was the lark, the herald of the morn,
no nightingale.
Look.
What envious streaks do lace
the severing clouds in yonder east.
Night's candles are burned out,
and jocund day stands tiptoe
on the misty mountain tops.
I must be gone and live, or stay and die.
Yon light is not daylight, I know it, I.
It is some meteor that the sun exhales
to be to thee this night a torchbearer,
and light thee on thy way to Mantua.
Therefore stay yet,
thou need'st not to be gone.
I am content, so thou wilt have it so.
I'll say yon gray is not the morning's eye.
Nor that is not the lark,
whose notes do beat the vaulty heaven
so high above our heads.
I have more care to stay than will to go.
Come, death, and welcome.
How is it, my soul?
Let's talk, it is not day.
It is, it is.
Hie hence, be gone, away.
It is the lark that sings so out of tune.
Oh, now be gone.
More light and light it grows.
Nurse.
Your lady mother is coming
to your chamber.
Day is broke. Be wary, look about.
Then, window, let day in,
and let life out.
Farewell.
Art thou gone so?
My lord, my love, my friend.
Oh, think'st thou
we shall ever meet again?
I doubt it not.
And all these woes
shall serve for sweet discourses
in our time to come.
O God.
I have an ill-divining soul.
Methinks I see thee, now thou art below,
as one dead in the bottom of a tomb.
Dry sorrow drinks our blood.
Adieu.
Why, how now, Juliet?
Evermore weeping
for your cousin's death?
What, wilt thou wash him
from his grave with tears?
And if thou couldst,
thou couldst not make him live.
Therefore, have done.
But now
I'll tell thee joyful tidings, girl.
And joy comes well in such a needy time.
What are they, I beseech your ladyship?
My child, early tomorrow morn
the gallant, young and noble gentleman,
the County Paris, at St. Peter's church,
shall happily make thee there
a joyful bride.
No!
By St. Peter's Church and Peter, too,
he shall not make me there a joyful bride!
I wonder at this haste. That I must wed
ere he that should be husband
comes to woo.
I pray you, tell my lord and father,
madam, I will not marry yet.
Here comes your father.
Tell him so yourself,
and see how he will take it at your hands.
How now, wife?
Have you deliver'd to her our decree?
Ay, sir, but she will none,
she gives you thanks.
Is she not proud?
Doth she not count her blessed,
unworthy as she is,
that we have wrought so worthy
a gentleman to be her bridegroom?
Proud can I never be of what I hate.
Proud me no prouds,
but go with Paris to St. Peter's church,
or I will drag thee on a hurdle thither.
Good father, I beseech you on my knees,
hear me with patience
but to speak a word.
Hang thee, young baggage.
Disobedient wretch!
I tell thee what, get thee to church,
or never after look me in the face.
Speak not, reply not, do not answer me.
God in heaven, bless her.
You are to blame, my lord, to rate her so.
Peace, you mumbling fool.
Utter your gravity o'er a gossip's bowl.
- For here we need it not.
- You are too hot!
God's bread! It makes me mad
to have a wretched puling fool
to answer, "I'll not wed. I cannot love.
I am too young. I pray you, pardon me."
Look to it, think on it.
I do not use to jest.
If you be mine, I'll give you to my friend.
If you be not, hang, beg,
starve, die in the street.
For, by my soul,
I'll ne'er acknowledge thee.
Is there no pity sitting in the clouds
that sees into the bottom of my grief?
Sweet my mother, cast me not away.
Delay this marriage for a month, a week.
Talk not to me, for I'll not speak a word.
Do as thou wilt, for I have done with thee!
O God!
O nurse.
How shall this be prevented?
What say'st thou?
Hast thou not a word of joy?
Some comfort, nurse.
Faith.
Faith, here it is.
Romeo is banished.
And all the world to nothing that he dares
ne'er come back to challenge you.
I think it best
you married with the county.
Oh, he's a lovely gentleman.
Romeo is a dish-clout to him.
Beshrew my very heart,
I think you are happy
in this second match,
for it excels your first.
Speak'st thou from thy heart?
Ay, and from my soul, too,
or else beshrew them both.
- Amen.
- What?
Thou hast comforted me marvelous much.
Go in and tell my lady I am gone,
having displeased my father,
to Laurence's cell,
to make confession and to be absolved.
Marry, I will. And this is wisely done.
Ancient damnation!
O most wicked fiend!
Go, counselor.
Thou and my bosom
henceforth shall be twain.
I'll to the friar, to know his remedy.
If all else fail, myself have power to die.
Sir Paris, the time is very short.
My father Capulet will have it so.
And I am nothing slow to slack his haste.
You say you do not know the lady's mind.
Uneven is the course, I like it not.
Immoderately she weeps
for Tybalt's death.
Her father counts it dangerous that
she doth give her sorrow so much sway,
and in his wisdom hastes our marriage.
Now do you know the reason of this haste.
Happily met, my lady and my wife.
Come you to make confession
to this father?
Do not deny to him that you love me.
I will confess to you that I love him.
So will you, I am sure, that you love me.
If I do so, it will be of more price,
being spoke behind your back,
than to your face.
Are you at leisure, holy father, now?
My lord, we must entreat the time alone.
God shield, I should disturb devotion.
Juliet, tomorrow early will I rouse you.
Till then, adieu.
And keep this holy kiss.
Oh, shut the door.
Come weep with me.
Past hope, past cure, past help.
Now, Juliet, I already know thy grief.
Tell me not, Friar, that thou hear'st of this,
unless thou tell me how I may prevent it.
God joined my heart and Romeo's,
thou our hands.
And ere this hand,
by thee to Romeo's sealed,
shall be the label to another deed,
or my true heart with treacherous revolt
turn to another,
this shall slay them both.
Hold, daughter.
I do spy a kind of hope.
lf, rather than to marry County Paris,
thou hast the strength of will
to slay thyself,
then is it likely
thou wilt undertake a thing like death?
And I will do it without fear or doubt,
to live an unstain'd wife to my sweet love.
Hold, then. Go home,
be merry, give consent to marry Paris.
Tonight look that thou lie alone.
Let not thy nurse lie with thee
in thy chamber.
Take thou this vial, being then in bed,
and this distilled liquor drink thou off.
When presently through all thy veins
shall run a cold and drowsy humor,
for no pulse, no warmth, no breath,
shall testify thou livest.
And in this borrow'd likeness
of shrunk death
thou shalt continue two-and-forty hours.
Now, when the bridegroom in the morning
comes to rouse thee from thy bed,
there art thou dead.
Then, as the manner of our country is,
in thy best robes uncover'd on the bier,
thou shalt be borne
to that same ancient vault
where all the kindred of the Capulets lie.
In the mean time,
shall Romeo by my letters know our drift,
and hither shall he come.
And he and I will watch thy waking,
and that very night
shall Romeo bear thee hence to Mantua.
Oh, give me, give me. Tell me not of fear.
Hold. Get you gone.
Be strong and prosperous in this resolve.
I'll send a friar with speed to Mantua
with my letters to thy lord.
Love give me strength.
Farewell, dear father.
Hence to Mantua.
Early in the morning, see thou deliver it.
Holy Reverend Friar, come, come with me.
- The infectious pestilence.
- Pestilence.
Pestilence.
- Pestilence!
Take heed! Take heed! Hold me not!
Take heed!
Ay, those attires are best,
but, gentle nurse, I pray thee,
leave me to myself tonight.
Need you my help?
No, madam.
So please you, let me now be left alone,
and let the nurse this night,
sit up with you,
for I am sure you have your hands full
all in this so sudden business.
Good night. Get thee to bed and rest,
for thou hast need.
Farewell.
God knows when we shall meet again.
I have a faint cold fear
thrill through my veins,
that almost freezes up the heat of life.
I'll call them back, to comfort me. Nurse!
What should she do here?
My dismal scene I needs must act alone.
What if this mixture do not work at all?
Shall I be married then
tomorrow morning?
No, no.
This shall forbid it.
Lie thou there.
What if it be a poison,
which the friar subtly hath minister'd
to have me dead
lest in this marriage
he should be dishonor'd
because he married me before to Romeo?
I fear it is,
and yet, methinks, it should not,
for he hath still been tried a holy man.
How if, when I am laid into the tomb,
I wake before the time
that Romeo come to redeem me?
There is a fearful point.
Shall I not then be stifled in the vault
to whose foul mouth
no healthsome air breathes in?
Or, if I live,
is it not very like the horrible conceit
of death and night
together with the terror of the place
where, for these many hundred years,
the bones of all my buried ancestors
are pack'd,
where bloody Tybalt, yet but green
in earth, lies festering in his shroud,
where as they say
at some hours in the night spirits resort.
Alack, alack, is it not like that I,
so early waking
what with loathsome smells and shrieks
like mandrakes torn out of the earth,
that living mortals, hearing them,
run mad.
O, if I wake, shall I not be distraught,
environed with all these hideous fears,
and madly play with my forefathers' joints
and pluck the mangled Tybalt
from his shroud?
And in this rage with some
great kinsman's bone, as with a club,
dash out my desperate brains?
O, look.
Methinks I see my cousin's ghost
seeking out Romeo, that did spit his body
upon a rapier's point.
Stay, Tybalt, stay.
Romeo, I come.
This do I drink to thee.
Hold.
Take these keys
and fetch more spices, nurse.
They call for dates and quinces
in the pastry.
Nurse! Wife!
What ho! What, nurse, I say.
Go waken Juliet!
Hie, make haste, make haste.
The bridegroom, he is come already.
Mistress! What, Mistress!
Juliet.
Fast, I warrant her, she.
Why, lamb.
Why, lady.
Fie, you slug-a-bed.
What, not a word?
Marry and amen, how sound she is asleep.
I needs must wake her.
Madam,
madam,
madam.
My lord!
My lady!
What noise is here?
What is the matter?
O me.
My child, my only life.
Help, help!
Help!
For shame, bring Juliet forth.
Her lord is come!
Alack the day.
She's dead.
Let me see her.
Death lies on her
like an untimely frost
upon the sweetest flower of all the field.
Hence, in haste. Farewell.
Help! Call help!
If I may trust the flattering truth of sleep,
my dreams presage
some joyful news at hand.
I dreamt my lady came
and found me dead.
Strange dream that gives a dead man
leave to think.
And breathed such life
with kisses in my lips
that I revived
and was an emperor.
Ah, me.
How sweet is love itself possessed.
When but love's shadows
are so rich in joy.
News from Verona.
How now, Balthasar?
Dost thou not bring me letters
from the friar?
How doth my lady? Is my father well?
How fares my Juliet?
That I ask again, for nothing can be ill
if she be well.
Then she is well, and nothing can be ill.
Her body sleeps in Capels' monument,
and her immortal part with angels lives.
Oh, pardon me for bringing these ill news.
Is it even so?
Then I defy you, stars.
Hire me post-horses. I will hence tonight.
I do beseech you, sir, have patience.
Your looks are pale and wild
and do import some misadventure.
Thou art deceived.
Leave me, and do the thing I bid thee do.
- Hast thou no letters to me from the friar?
- No, my good lord.
No matter.
Get thee gone, hire those horses.
I'll be with thee straight.
Well, Juliet,
I will lie with thee tonight.
Apothecary.
Come hither, man.
I see that thou art poor.
Here is 40 ducats.
Let me have a dram of poison,
such soon-speeding gear as will disperse
itself through all the veins
that the life-weary taker may fall dead.
Such mortal drugs I have,
but Mantua's law is death
to any he that utters them.
Art thou so bare and full of wretchedness
and fear'st to die?
The world is not thy friend
nor the world's law.
The world affords no law
to make thee rich.
Then be not poor, but break it. Take this.
My poverty but not my will consent.
I pay thy poverty and not thy will.
Put this in any liquid thing you will
and drink it off.
And if you had the strength of 20 men,
it would dispatch you straight.
Here is thy gold,
worse poison to men's souls,
doing more murder
in this loathsome world
than these poor compounds
that thou may'st not sell.
I sell thee poison,
thou hast sold me none.
Who bare my letter then to Romeo?
I could not send it,
nor get a messenger to bring it thee,
so fearful were they of infection.
Unhappy fortune.
By my brotherhood, that letter,
the neglecting of it may do much danger.
Now must I to the monument alone.
Within this three hours
will fair Juliet wake.
She will beshrew me much that Romeo
hath had no notice of these accidents.
Sweet flower,
with flowers thy bridal bed I strew.
O woe, thy canopy is dust and stone.
Give me the light.
Upon thy life I charge thee,
whate'er thou hear'st or see'st,
stand all aloof,
and do not interrupt me in my course.
I will be gone, sir, and not trouble you.
So shalt thou show me friendship.
Take thou that.
Live and be prosperous.
And farewell, good fellow.
Thou detestable maw,
thou womb of death,
gorged with the dearest morsel
of the earth.
Thus I enforce thy rotten jaws to open,
and, in despite,
I'll cram thee with more food.
Stop thy unhallowed toil, vile Montague!
Can vengeance be pursued
further than death?
Condemned villain, I do apprehend thee!
Obey and go with me, for thou must die!
I must, indeed,
and therefore came I hither.
I beseech thee, youth, put not another sin
upon my head by urging me to fury.
Stay not, be gone. Live!
And hereafter say a madman's mercy
bade thee run away.
I do defy thy conjurations
and apprehend thee for a villain here!
Give me thy hand,
one writ with me
in sour misfortune's book.
I'll bury thee in a triumphant grave.
A grave?
Oh, no, a lantern, slaughter'd youth,
for here lies Juliet,
and her beauty makes this vault
a feasting presence full of light.
Death, lie thou there,
by a dead man interred.
Oh, my love, my wife.
Death that hath suck'd the honey
of thy breath
hath had no power yet upon thy beauty.
Thou art not conquered.
Beauty's ensign yet
is crimson in thy lips and in thy cheeks,
and death's pale flag
is not advanced there.
Ah, dear Juliet, I still will stay with thee
and never from this palace of dim night
depart again.
Here will I set up my everlasting rest
and shake the yoke of inauspicious stars
from this world-wearied flesh.
Eyes, look your last.
Arms, take your last embrace.
And, lips, O you the doors of breath,
seal with a righteous kiss
a dateless bargain to engrossing death.
Come, bitter conduct,
come, unsavory guide.
Thou desperate pilot, now at once run on
the dashing rocks thy sea-sick weary bark.
Here's to my love.
Oh, true Apothecary, thy drugs are quick.
Thus with a kiss
I die.
Romeo.
Alack, alack, what blood is this?
What mean these masterless
and gory swords
to lie discolor'd by this place of peace?
Oh, what an unkind hour
is guilty of this lamentable chance?
O comfortable friar,
where is my lord?
I do remember well where I should be,
and there I am.
Where is my Romeo?
Lady,
come from that nest of death,
contagion, and unnatural sleep.
A greater power than we can contradict
hath thwarted our intents.
Come, come away.
Thy husband there lies dead.
Stay not to question,
for the watch is coming.
Come, good Juliet. I dare no longer stay.
Go, get thee hence,
for I will not away.
O churl.
Drunk all, and left no friendly drop
to help me after.
I will kiss thy lips. Haply,
some poison yet doth hang on them.
Thy lips are warm.
Lead, boy. Which way?
Yea, noise?
Then I'll be brief.
Oh, happy dagger.
This is thy sheath.
There rust,
and let me die.
Go tell the Prince.
Run to the Capulets!
Raise up the Montagues.
Capulet. Montague.
See what a scourge is laid upon your hate,
that heaven finds means
to kill your joys with love.
And I, for winking at your discords, too,
have lost a brace of kinsmen.
All are punished.
O brother Montague, give me thy hand.
This is my daughter's jointure,
for no more can I demand.
But I can give thee more.
For I will raise her statue in pure gold.
That while Verona by that name is known
there shall no figure at such rate be set
as that of true and faithful Juliet.
As rich shall Romeo by his lady lie,
poor sacrifices of our enmity.
A glooming peace this morning
with it brings.
The sun for sorrow will not show his head.
For never was a story of more woe
than this of Juliet and her Romeo.